Guide to the William O. Douglas Collection 1920-1980
Whitman College and Northwest Archives
- Papers created and collected by Douglas, Series 1; 21 boxes
  - Speeches, 1936-1973; Sub-Series 7
    - Administrative Government, Undated (Box-folder 18/6)
    - Administrative Law (ICC), Undated (Box-folder 18/7)
    - Unknown, Undated (Box-folder 18/9)
    - SEC Investments and the Role of Companies, Missing pgs. 1-2, Undated (Box-folder 18/12)
    - Sec Changes in the Stock Market, Missing pg. 1, Undated (Box-folder 18/13)
    - SEC: Public Utility Act of 1935, Undated (Box-folder 18/14)
    - Foreign Policy: National War College (Outline), Undated (Box-folder 18/15)
    - Foreign Policy: National War College, Undated (Box-folder 18/16)
    - Vietnam, Undated (Box-folder 18/17)
    - Introduction for Judge Edward S. Silver at Hebrew University, Undated (Box-folder 18/18)
- Material collected by Leonard Jansen, Series 2
  - Articles and memorabilia on Douglas, Sub-Series 1
    - "The Douglas Letters" by Tom Scriber in Whitman Magazine, Fall 1988 (Box-folder 23/1)
    - "My Recollections of Mr. Justice W.O. Douglas," by L.F. Jansen, 1989 (Box-folder 23/2)
    - "Douglas Letters"; The News Tribune and Oregonian, 1987 (Box-folder 23/3)
    - Introduction, 4/10/1994 (Box-folder 23/4)
    - The Late Justice Douglas Still Creates News, The Times San Mateo, 3/20/1989 (Box-folder 23/5)
    - Douglas Then and Now, ABA Journal, 11/1/1987 (Box-folder 23/6)
    - Douglas Still Stirs Up Passion, 2/12/1989 (Box-folder 23/7)
    - Douglas, W.O., Jr.; Article about Death, 2/22/1989 (Box-folder 23/8)
    - W.O.D. Memorial Scholarship, WC, Undated (Box-folder 23/9)
    - W.O.D. Commemorative Symposium, Seattle, WA. 1939- 1989/ Program and Invitation, 4/15/1989 (Box-folder 23/10)
    - Letter to Public from Deal, David, 10/25/1990 (Box-folder 23/11)
    - 9 Presentations RE Douglas/ W.O.D. Institute, 4/15/1989 (Box-folder 23/12)
    - A Tribute to Mr.Justice W.O. Douglas by Brennan, W. I./ WA Law Review, 1980 (Box-folder 23/13)
    - Justice Douglas' Advice to the Young: Occupy High Ground, by Fortas, Abe/ The Century Magazine, March/April 1979 (Box-folder 23/14)
    - excerpt from The Brethren by Woodward, Bob Armstrong, Scott, 1979 (Box-folder 23/15)
    - Justice William O. Douglas by Duram, James C., Undated (Box-folder 23/16)
    - Summary of Biography by Hoyt, Edwin P., Undated (Box-folder 23/17)
    - Douglas Letters, Urofsky, Melvin, Undated (Box-folder 23/18)
    - Yakima Memorial Takes Shape/ WA State Bar News, April 1981 (Box-folder 23/19)
    - Address, 4/3/1959 (Box-folder 23/20)
    - The Origins of W.O.Douglas's Jurisprudence, Undated (Box-folder 23/21)
    - Letters: Copies w/o Originals or Duplicate from Len Jansen, Undated (Box-folder 23/22)
    - WOD " Independent Journey" (Box-folder 24/1)
    - WOD Letters Etc. (Box-folder 24/2)
    - WOD Keepsakes (Box-folder 24/3)
    - Douglas (Box-folder 24/4)
    - "Some Glimpses of WOD" (Box-folder 24/5)
    - Columbia Law School: Douglas Memorial (Box-folder 24/6)
    - WOD Correspondence: Cathy- Mercedes (Box-folder 24/7)
    - Recollections (Box-folder 24/8)
    - Biographical Data, Articles by (Box-folder 24/9)
    - Whitman Symposium- 1998 (Box-folder 24/10)
    - Decline and Death (Box-folder 24/11)
    - Mens Club (Box-folder 24/12)
  - Correspondence between Jansen and Douglas, Sub-Series 2; 4 binders
    - Binder: Douglas, W.O. 1940-1959; Jansen, Len 1952-1973
    - Binder: Copies of Letters, Jansen to Douglas 12/1/1952 to 10/15/1979
    - Binder: Douglas to Jansen, 1960-1979
    - Binder: Jansen, Len, 1962-1979
  - William O. Douglas 1898-1980, Sub-Series 3
    - Scrapbook
- Materials collected by Whitman College, Series 3
  - Whitman College file on W.O.Douglas, Sub-Series 1
    - Remarks of the President to a Joint Session of the Congress, 3/15/1965 (Box-folder 22/1)
    - Sesquicentennical Celebration of the Supreme Court of the US, 2/1/1940 (Box-folder 22/2)
    - Certificate of Authenticity: W.O.D. Hand-cast Bust by Wendy M. Ross, # 38, 12/7/1977 (Box-folder 22/3)
    - Douglas, William O. :Play "Not Guilty" 3 Acts, Undated (Box-folder 22/4)
    - Play: "The Devil and the Lord" Revised, 1/31/1972 (Box-folder 22/5)
    - Unlabeled Folder (Box-folder 22/6)
      - Program, Dedication of Douglas Hall, 10/15/1980
      - Memorial Articles, Various
      - WA State Bar News: Yakima Memorial, April 1981
      - Articles on Justice's Death, 1980
      - Articles on Cathy Douglas, 4th wife, Various
      - "A Wilderness Bill of Rights", by W.O.D., December 1961
    - Douglas, William O.: Named to Federal Securities and Exchange Commission, 1935-1936 (Box-folder 22/7)
    - Convocation Speech at Whitman, 9/15/1939 (Box-folder 22/8)
    - Letter to and From Chester C. Maxey, 2/3,5/1958 (Box-folder 22/9)
    - Tributes to Honorable William O. Douglas: Hard Cover Edition, 1975 (Box-folder 22/10)
    - Clippings, Various (Box-folder 22/11)
    - Rotaty Club File, Undated (Box-folder 22/12)
    - Correspondence to Whitman, circa 1940 (Box-folder 22/13)
    - Douglas, William O., Various (Box-folder 22/14)
      - Federal Bar News, A Tribute to Justice William O. Douglas, March 1980
      - "Justice Tells of his Travels through the Explosive Middle East…"
      - Justice Douglas's Son Married
      - Articles on Horse Accident
      - Articles on C O Canal Hike
      - "A Boy debator Who Made the Top Team: That Fellow Douglas" by John H. Crider
      - Misc. Newspaper Articles
    - Whitman College transcript and application, 1916-1920 (Box-folder 22/15)
    - William O. Douglas Alumni File Class of 1920 (Box 25)
      - -WC Pioneer Articles RE W.O.D.
      - -Newspaper Articles
      - -World Issues, The William O. Douglas Inquiry
      - -Articles on "Mountain" a Play about W.O.D.
      - -W.O.D. Alumni Card
      - -Article RE. Gift of Presidents' Signatures to WC
      - -Biographical Sketches
      - -Articles in W.O.D.'s death
      - -American Bar Association, Mr. Justice Douglas Reaches a Milestone
      - -Misc. Newspaper Articles RE. W.O.D.
      - -Misc. Biographical Sketches
      - Photocopies of Articles
      - The Intermountain Observer, A Traveler's Guide, Idaho
      - Articles on Former Wives
      - Article of W.O.D. Jr. Mime Acting
      - The Living Wilderness, Spring 1954
      - 1971 WC Alumni Directory, W.O.D.
      - 1959 WC Alumni Directory
      - Photocopy of Douglas Books Category
      - Clippings Tear Sheets, 1949
      - Clippings Tear Sheets, 1950
      - Clippings Tear Sheets, 1951
      - Clippings Tear Sheets, 1952
      - Clippings Tear Sheets, 1953
      - The Supreme Court Justices, A Biographical Dictionary
      - Remembrances of William O. Douglas by His Friends and Associates
      - Southern California Law Review, Symposium Law and Technology, preface by W.O.D.
      - The American Mercury, Bill Douglas: American, by Fres Rodell, December 1945
      - Yale Law Journal A Symposium on Credit for the Urban Employee, February 1933
      - W.O.D.'s articles from American the Beautiful, Readers Digest
      - Article on W.O.D. Siblings to Graduate from Whitman College, March 22, 1939
      - Articles on Douglas's Horse Injury
      - Articles on Marriage to 24-year-old College Student
      - Artilces re: Douglas Books
      - Address before the 10th Annual Convention of the Congress of Industrial Organizations, November 24, 1948
      - W.O.D. Biography: Bulger and Fairhaven College
  - Memorabilia collected by Whitman College, Sub-Series 2 (Box 26)
    - Notebook listing periodical articles about Douglas
    - Notebook listing periodical articles by Douglas
    - Box of newspaper clippings about Douglas
    - The Bible and the Schools, LP by Douglas explaining Supreme Court decisions
    - Framed photograph of Supreme Court Building autographed by Douglas
    - Framed autographed photograph of Douglas
    - Framed caricature of Douglas
    - My Shangri-La, framed essay about Yakima Valley by Douglas
    - Nameplate and stand "Supreme Court Justice William O. Douglas, 1898-1980"
- Materials Collected by David Allard, Series 4
  - Bill of Rights Course, Articles about, 1965 (Box-folder 27/1)
  - Bill of Rights Course, Handbooks, 1965 (Box-folder 27/2)
  - Bill of Rights Course, Speech by Douglas, March 9, 1965 (Box-folder 27/3)
  - Photographs of the Supreme Court Justices, 1967-1972 (Box-folder 27/4)